欢迎回来，现在是凝聚态课程的第十七讲
welcome back this is now the seventeenth
lecture of the condensed matter course
当我们上次离开时​​，我们谈论的是乐队的结构，
when we left off last time we were
talking about band structure and we were
讨论导带，空穴和价带中的电子，以及
talking about electrons in conduction
bands and holes and valence bands and
今天我们要做的是，首先要考虑如何
what we're going to do today is we're
going to start by thinking about how
电子和导带以及价带中的空穴四处移动，所以让我们
electrons and conduction bands and holes
in valence bands move around so let's
首先画一个导带的底部，所以我们有一些E和
start by drawing the bottom of a
conduction band so we have some E and
一些K，并且导带将会有一些二次最小值
some K and there's going to be some
quadratic minimum of a conduction band
让我们称此点为发生底部的位置
let's call this point here came in where
the bottom occurs and this point here
我们将其称为不是导带底部的能量
we'll call it e not the energy of the
bottom of the conduction band very
通常，也许我会在这里写出来，我们可以写
generally maybe I'll write it over here
very generally we can we can write for
在带的底部附近的电子，E大约为e
an electron in the near the bottom of
the band that E is approximately e
零加泰勒展开式d平方e DK平方乘以K减去K min
nought plus just the Taylor expansion d
squared e DK squared times K minus K min
平方其他术语，我们将忽略，鉴于此，我们将定义一个
squared maybe other terms which we'll
ignore and given this we will define an
有效质量电子有效质量电子有效质量有效
effective mass an electron effective
mass electron effective mass effective
质量M star通过m星电子上的1等于H bar上的1
mass M star I'm star sub electron via 1
over m star electron equals 1 over H bar
平方d平方e DK平方使得没有能量加通常的H
squared d squared e DK squared such that
the energy is e naught plus the usual H
bar平方K减去K min平方2m电子星，现在看起来非常
bar squared K minus K min squared over
2m electron star now this looks very
就像自由电子一样，除了动量之外，波矢应该是
much like a free electron except the
momentum the the wave vector should be
相对于它们的测量，通常动量的最小值
measured with respect to them wherever
the minimum in the momentum is the usual
现在给定自由电子抛物线，我们还可以计算实际给定的任何
free electron parabola now given this we
can also calculate actually given any
在这个频带中，电子的能量形式
form of the energy of the of the
electron in this in this band we can
一般写组速度v组
write a group velocity v group very
generally is deal
衰减是群速度的一般表达，因为我们可以重放欧米茄
decay that's a general expression for a
group velocity since we can replay Omega
超过H bar倍乘以能源DK的倍数，这就是一般关系
by 1 over H bar times times and energy
de DK this is the general relationship
在我们的情况下，对于一个带中电子的群速度，将使用
for the group velocity of an electron in
a band in our case it will be using this
在这里的弥散度将是H Bar K减去电子m星上的K min
dispersion up here it will be H Bar K
minus K min over m star of the electron
因此，这意味着如果您将图片移到这里
so it means that if you have this
picture over here if you if you move the
电子在最小值的右边，然后电子在右边移动
electron to the right of the minimum
then the electron is moving to the right
如果将电子移至最小值的左侧，则电子正在移动
if you move the electron to the left of
the minimum then the electron is moving
左边是事实，与青铜器中最小的位置无关
to the left this is true independent of
where in the bronz own the minimum
发生，所以真正的问题是您相对于
occurs so really the issue is where are
your position with respect to the
如果要弄清楚小组速度现在是哪个方向，则为最小值
minimum if you want to figure out which
direction your group velocity is now
有一些注意事项，在此不写
there are a couple of caveats they don't
write them here caveats one generally
有效质量是正确的这个质量可能是各向异性质量
effective mass is right this mass is
maybe anisotropic masses can be
各向异性意味着能量可能在所有方向上都是抛物线形的
anisotropic meaning that the energy is
it may be parabolic in all directions
但是取决于您选择曲率的方向是
but depending on which crystal direction
you choose the curvature may be
不同的是，如果您有四角形，这是很自然的
different this is sort of natural if you
have something like a tetra angle
水晶，在不同的方向上，轴的长度不同
crystal where the axes are different
lengths in the different directions you
可能期望在不同位移K中的能量曲率
might expect that the curvature of the
energy in the different displacing K in
不同的方向可能会有所不同，的确如此
the different directions might be
different and indeed it often is so one
不得不担心这样一个事实，取决于您走的是哪种方式
has to worry about the fact that
depending on which way you're going your
有效质量似乎有所不同，我们通常会忽略这一点，因此请忽略
effective mass may seem different we're
going to ignore this generally so ignore
这种并发症，但更普遍的是，您应该知道它确实会发生
this complication but more generally you
should be aware that it does occur the
您应该知道的第二种并发症是，您可以
second complication that you should be
aware and it occurs is you can have
如果在两个极小值的情况下绘制E对K的情况
situations if you plot E versus K in a
situation where there are two minima
以完全相同的能量发生
that occur at exactly the same energy
this e
这样导带的最小值可以出现在
so that the minimum of the conduction
band can occur at two places in the
青铜拥有k1和k2，由于明显的原因，它们被称为山谷
bronz own k1 and k2 these are known as
valleys valleys for obvious reason and
这看起来好像不是很不寻常的事情
this may look like it's not something
that's very unusual to have happen that
你只是一个巧合，以至于发生相同能量的最小值
you have just such a coincidence that
the minima that the same energy occurs
在青铜器中至少有两个地方，但实际上
at the minimum in two places in the
bronz own but in fact it's actually
由于晶体的对称性，因此很常见
quite common to have this be due to
symmetries of the crystal so generally
如果晶体特别对称，则会发生这种情况，您将拥有两个
this will happen if the crystal is
particularly symmetric you'll have two
铜带本身或两个不同点的导带中的最小值
minimum in the conduction band at two
different points in the bronz own or
甚至青铜拥有四个不同点甚至六个不同点
even four different points or even six
different points of the bronze own so
您必须跟踪电子是否在此最小值或以下
you have to keep track of whether the
electron is in this minimum or this
最低要求，但一般规则适用，如果您将自己从
minimum but the general rule applies
that if you displace yourself from the
如果移至最小，则向右移动
minimum to the right you're moving to
the right if you displace yourself from
在最小值的左边减去两个最小值，然后向左移动
two the minimum to the left of the
minimum then you're moving to the left
好吧，现在最后一点我们通常是
okay
now the final point generally we're
实际上，我们将忽略这种复杂性，也忽略这种复杂性
actually we're going to ignore this
complication also ignore this as well
请注意，有时会发生最终的并发症
just be aware that it sometimes occurs
the final complication is perhaps a much
更重要的并发症是如果您具有能带结构，这是青铜色
more important complication if you have
a band structure here's a bronze own if
您具有像我们之前绘制的紧密结合带结构那样的带结构
you have a band structure like the tight
binding band structures we drew before
看起来像这样，通常有效质量是由第二个给定的
that looks like this the generally the
effective mass is given by the second
能量相对于K的导数，因此将意味着
derivative of the energy with respect to
K so that would mean that M star of the
这里的电子大于零，但是在这里电子的M星将是
electron here is greater than zero but
up here M star of the electron would be
小于零，对于粒子具有负质量似乎很奇怪，但是
less than zero which seems rather odd to
have a negative mass for a particle but
我们稍后会看到这实际上很有道理，而实际上我们
we'll see in a moment that actually
makes quite a bit of sense and really we
应该认为电子的质量是负数
should think of the mass of the electron
as being negative the general definition
电子的质量超过H bar平方d平方e DK平方
that the mass of the electron one over H
bar squared d squared e DK squared will
始终保持不变，这就是我们应该一直认为的有效质量
always hold and that's what we should
always think of as the effective mass
好，到目前为止，这很好，这是容易的部分，困难的部分是当我们开始时
okay so far so good this was the easy
part the hard part is when we start
考虑价带顶部的孔
thinking about holes at the top of a
valence band
所以变得困难的原因是-迹象会回来咬你
so the reason it gets hard is because -
signs will come back and bite you one
或其他方式，因此很难跟踪减号并
way or the other so it's really hard to
keep track of the minus signs and to
更糟糕的是，有些书将减号放在不同的位置，所以您
make matters worse some books put the
minus signs in different places so you
知道这是这些情况之一，只要您知道自己在做什么
know this is one of these situations
where as long as you know what you're
如果您有减号的偶数，则可以移动减号
doing you can move the minus sign around
if you have the even number of minus
一天结束时，您会得到正确的答案，但是我要做什么
signs at the end of the day you've got
the right answer but what I'm going to
告诉你我所认为的最自然的方法来思考放置位置
tell you is what I think is the most
natural way to think of where you put
减号，我认为大多数书籍对此都表示同意，但并非全部如此
the minus signs and I think most books
agree with me on this but not all so be
警告说，这是顶部有孔的情况
warned about that so this is the
situation with holes at the top of
价带处于乐队顶部，所以这意味着在这里我们发现了这个奇数
valence bands top of bands so so that
means up here where we found this odd
当我们考虑电子时，电子的质量为负
result that the mass of the electron is
negative when we're thinking about the
像在那边这样的乐队的顶部，我们通常会发现这个奇怪的结果
top of a band like over there where we
found this odd result we're usually
当我们在乐队的顶部时，想着一个几乎充满的乐队，
thinking when we're at the top of the
band about a nearly filled band and
价带几乎满了，所以我们将再次绘制E与K，我们会想象
nearly filled valence band so we'll draw
again E versus K and we'll imagine that
我们有一些乐队的顶部，这些乐队大部分都充满了，我们会考虑的
we have the top of some band which is
mostly filled and we'll think about okay
我们将其放置在K Max上，好吧，我们将其称为e v-不在这里，我们
we'll put this at K Max and okay and we
will call this e v-not also up here we
想像一下，如果我们将电子放在该能带的顶部，那是一种能量
imagine if we put an electron up at the
top of this band somewhere it's a energy
会没事的，所以对于孔的情况，带子顶部带子顶部的能量
is going to be okay so for the case of
holes top a band top a band the energy
保持电子的追踪非常好
of an electron e electron it's really
good to keep keeping your head track of
不管是在谈论电子能量还是空穴能量，因为
whether you're talking about an electron
energy or a hole energy because you'll
看到他们将在一秒钟内变得困惑，所以电子能量如果
see that they're going to get confused
in a second so the electron energy if
您将电子放在频带的顶部附近，这将是一些容易的行加1/2
you put an electron near the top of the
band that will be some easy row plus 1/2
d平方e DK平方乘以K减去K max平方与它完全相同
d squared e DK squared times K minus K
max squared exactly the same way as it
以前是，但现在这里的数量为负，因此小于零，
这就是为什么我们应该认为这里的电子质量是负数
this is why we should think of the mass
of the electron here as being a negative
数量，因为当您远离
quantity because the
goes down as you go away from the
最大，所以在这里我们要做的是使我们的生活更简单一些
maximum so here what we're going to do
to make our life a little bit simpler is
定义孔的质量将孔的质量定义为整个m的H bar平方
to define a mass of a hole define mass
of hole to be H bar squared over m whole
恒星为负d平方e为电子DK平方，所以这东西在这里
star is minus d squared e for the
electron DK squared so this thing here
大于零在乐队的顶部乐队，你会注意到
is greater than zero at top a band
top of band and you will notice from
将此定义与上面的定义（孔的M星）进行比较
comparing this definition to the above
definition that the M star of the hole
实际上等于负号，电子的恒星还可以，所以在这里
is actually equal to minus and the star
of the electron okay so up here where
电子的质量似乎为负，我们已经定义了
the mass of the electron appears to be
negative we've defined the mass of the
现在是负号，为什么这样做才有意义，为什么我们
hole to be minus of that now why is it
that this makes sense to do why is it we
应该将孔的质量定义为电子质量的负数，并且
should define the mass of a hole to be
negative of the mass of the electron and
为什么它应该是孔的一部分在化合价的顶部为正
why would should it be part of the hole
be positive at the top of the valence
乐队，让我们考虑一下，所以在这里我们有相同的顶部
band so let's think about this for a
second so here we have the same top of
价带我们想象整个价带被填充，除了一个
the valence band we imagine the whole
valence band is filled except for one
我们将其放在乐队顶部的孔
hole which we're putting at the top of
the band here
好吧，所以孔的能量是恒定的，你不会在旋转
okay so the energy of the hole e hole be
some constant you're not twiddle and
那么我们想找出随着我们
then we want to find out how does the
energy of this hole change as we
将其从乐队的顶部移开，所以让我们在这里想象这一点
displace it from the top of the band so
let's imagine this point here just so we
不必随身携带这些K Max，再来吧，让我们决定一下
don't have to carry around these K Max's
and came ins anymore let's decide this
这里的点是K等于零，因为我们将K替换为
point here is K equals zero as we
displace K from this is just for
简单起见，它不一定是K等于零，但让我们想象一下它是
simplicity it doesn't have to be a K
equals zero but let's imagine it is
让我们问一下，当您从顶部移开孔时，能量会发生什么变化
let's ask what happens to the energy as
you displace the hole from the top of
乐队，所以当您这样做时，我们将把孔从这里移到这里
the band so we're going to move the hole
from here to here well when you do that
能量实际上从此上升了
the energy actually has gone up from
this
将整个乐队放在乐队的顶端为什么将其写成H条
placing the whole from the top of the
band why is that well write it as H bar
我一直都在平方M星，如果我们从
squared to M star whole times I guess K
squared here if we're displacing it from
K等于零是当我们置换整体时能量上升的原因
K equals zero the reason that the energy
has gone up when we displace the whole
从带的顶部开始是因为电子正试图到达最低的
from the top of the band is because the
electrons are trying to go to the lowest
可能的能量孔试图冒出最大的能量
energy possible the holes try to bubble
up to the highest energy possible it's
就像是一个气袋或气泡，或者像在水下推气球一样
like it's like an air pocket or a bubble
or like pushing a balloon underwater if
你把这个气球带到这里，然后把它推到水下，这花了你很多的精力
you take this balloon here and you push
it underwater that costs you energy it
花了你正能量去把这个洞推到下面
costs you positive energy to take this
hole and push it underneath the
电子，因为电子想要尽可能降低能量是
electrons because the electrons want to
go to the lowest energy possible is that
很明显，这就是直觉，为什么你应该考虑
clear that's the intuition why it is
that you should think of the mass of the
孔是正的，因为当您将其从乐队的顶部移开时
hole as being positive because when you
displace it from the top of the band it
花费你积极的精力远离乐队的顶峰
costs you positive energy to move away
from the top of the band so far so good
好的，好的，所以这是易于跟踪的迹象，但迹象越来越多
okay good all right so that's the easy
sign to keep track of but signs get more
复杂的让我们问一个孔的动量什么是孔的动量
complicated let's ask about the momentum
of a hole what is the momentum of a hole
一个洞的动量和一个思考这个问题的好方法是意识到
momentum of a hole and a good way to
think about this is to realize that a
填充带填充带没有动量没有晶体动量没有晶体
filled band filled band has no momentum
has no crystal momentum no crystal
动量没有电流惰性，根本没有晶体动量，所以如果我们想
momentum carry no current inert has no
crystal momentum at all so if we want to
知道乐队顶部的一个洞的动量是多少，让我们想象一下
know what the momentum is of a hole in
the top of the band let's imagine here's
我们的乐队除了一个状态是
our band we fill the entire band like
this except for one state which is
像这样的状态从AK失踪了我们想像这个洞
missing out of AK a state like this we
imagine taking this hole this missing
乐队中的粒子，如果我们将其添加到一个空的乐队中
particle from the band if we add it to a
band that's empty except for that one
电子放置在这个加号等于填充带等于填充带
electron placed in then this Plus this
equals a filled band equals filled band
填充文件填充带，所以动量等于总动量
filled file filled band
so momentum so total momentum equals
零总h-bar K等于零好吧，所以这两个的总和
zero total h-bar K equals zero okay so
the sum of these two put together the
无孔的填充带，再加上空带
filled band with the absence of the hole
plus the empty band with this one
电子对不起已满的供应商，缺少该电子再加上空的电子
electron sorry the filled vendor the
absence of this electron plus the empty
当您将它们的总和放在一起时，带存在这个电子
band with the presence of this electron
when you put them together their total
动量将为零，所以我们有h-bar K
momentum is going to be zero so what we
have then is h-bar K for the hole over
这里加上电子的h-bar K应该在这里应该给我们
here plus h-bar K for the electron
should which is over here should give us
到目前为止，总数为零，这意味着H Bar K为一个孔
a total of zero so far so good
so that means that H Bar K for a hole
对于丢失的电子，它必须为负h-bar K，所以这是一种很好的方法
must be minus h-bar K for the missing
electron okay so that's a good way to
跟踪孔的动量应该是什么
keep track of what the momentum of a
hole should be there's one of these
令人困惑的减号现在让我们考虑一下这是什么速度
confusing minus signs now let's think
about given this what the velocity is of
这些东西的顶部实际上是一个洞
a hole at the top of them these things
are all actually going to be end up
很重要，因为您需要知道电子或空穴的方向
being important because you need to know
which way the electrons or the holes are
移动跟踪它，以了解带底部的电子
moving keeping track of it for an
electron at the bottom of the band
一切似乎都很自然，但是乐队顶部的一个洞开始了
everything seems very natural but a hole
at the top of the band everything starts
变得困惑，所以正确地跟踪这些很重要，所以让我们
getting confused so it's important to
keep track of these correctly so let's
考虑带子顶部的孔洞速度，所以我们再次开始
think about velocity of hole at top of
band at top of band so again we start
带的能量在带的顶部，所以不减H
with the energy for the electron at the
top of the band so that's not minus H
条形平方K平方K电子平方2m星孔好吧，为什么我
bar squared K squared K electron squared
over 2m star hole okay now why did I
以此方式绘制，使M星孔的能量大于零。
draw it this way so M star hole is
greater than zero the energy for the
电子随着远离K的电子动量增加而减小
electron decreases as you increase the
momentum of the electron away from K
等于零，带正在向下弯曲，因此电子的能量为
equals zero the band is curving down so
the energy for the electron is
降低组速度然后总是
decreasing
the group velocity then which is always
在H bar D上为1，所以这是电子D电子DJ的群速度
1 over H bar D so this is a group
velocity for the electron D electron DJ
因此，电子在整个m星或整个M星上减去h-bar K电子
electron is then minus h-bar K electron
over m star whole or since M star whole
是负M星电子，我们可以将其写为m星上的H Bar K e
is minus M star the electron we can
write this as H Bar K e over m star
电子，但M星电子小于零，所以这意味着如果我
electron but M star electron is is less
than zero so what this means is if I
如果我有一个像这样的空带并且在顶部附近有一个电子
have a if I had an empty band like this
and I had an electron here near the top
该带的速度实际上是这个电子的速度B
of the band the velocity of this
electron is actually going this way B
小组正朝着手套走，因为您可以将其视为
group is going this way right the mitt
because you can think of that as the
电子质量趋于负是因为负
electron mass is going negative is
negative because of the negative
因此，群速度实际上与
curvature so the group velocity is
actually in the opposite direction as
波矢好吧，我知道是我知道这令人困惑，但是你知道你是否
the wave vector okay I know it's I know
it's confusing but but you know if you
只需仔细跟踪迹象，一切都会正确，让我们
just keep track of the signs carefully
everything comes out correct let's
如果我们用术语来考虑的话，可以将其与能源的情况进行比较
compare that to the energy to the
situation if we think about it in terms
孔的能量，所以靠近带顶部的孔的能量是恒定的
of holes so the energy of a hole near
the top of the band is some constant
再加上h bar平方K整平方超过2m星整，所以洞的能量
plus h bar squared K whole squared over
2m star whole so the energy of the hole
随着您远离频段顶部而增加其动量而增加，因此
increases as you increase its momentum
away from the top of the band so the
组速度V组整体等于H之上de整体DK整体等于H
group velocity V group whole equals one
over H bar de whole DK whole equals H
K整体超过m星整体，而K整体我们刚刚决定是同一件事
Bar K whole over m star whole and K
whole we just decided is the same thing
因为电子的负K等于负KH bar H Bar K
as minus K for the electron so this is
the same thing as minus K H bar H Bar K
电子在毫米星孔上，这实际上与我们刚刚计算的相同
electron over mm star hole which is in
fact the same thing we just calculated
在这里，这里的意思是，如果我们有一个像这样的充满乐队
up here so the point here is that if we
have a filled band like this and one
空状态，这里的群速度朝这个方向
empty state here the group velocity of
that is going in this direction
同样，这是一个非常重要的原则，将再次出现
as well this is an extremely important
principle that will come back many times
或至少几次，但一个状态的速度
or at least several times but the
velocity of a state the velocity of an
轨道的轨道独立于该轨道是否为
orbital of an orbital orbital is
independent of whether that orbital is
填充轨道是否已填充，这样一堆就可以想到它
filled whether the orbital is filled so
you can think of it as you have a bunch
系统中的轨道数，并且轨道可以具有一定的速度
of orbitals in your system and the
orbitals have some velocity you can put
在那个轨道上的电子，电子将随着
an electron in that orbital and the
electron will move with that out with
那个速度，如果你从轨道上移走电子，它仍然是轨道
that velocity if you remove the electron
from that orbital it's still the orbital
仍然以相同的速度运动，只是其中没有电子
is still moving with the same velocity
it's just there's no electron in it okay
所以这是一个重要的原则，实际上
so this is kind of an important
principle which sort of it it actually
即使我们想到您就知道我们
makes a very good amount of sense even
when we think about you know the we
考虑氢原子或我们考虑这些轨道的某些事物
think about hydrogen atom or something
we think about these orbitals being
那里是否有电子存在于轨道和轨道中
there whether or not the there's an
electron in the orbital and the orbitals
可以以一定速度移动，它们仍然在那里并移动
can be moving with some velocity and
they're still there and moving
不管我们放电子还是不放电子
independent of whether we put the
electron in or we didn't put the
电子没问题，好吧，现在让我们实际尝试掌握我们学到的知识
electron in okay all right so let's now
actually try to take what we've learned
并计算一些电子动力学和空穴动力学
and calculate some dynamics dynamics of
electrons and holes dynamics of
电子和空穴的乔恩氏和空穴以及最简单的方法
electrons and holes
jon's and holes and the simplest way to
处理动力学是我们开始考虑提请的术语
handle dynamics is what we started the
term with which is to think about drew
回到理论上，所以我们将在数周后回到juda理论上，所以让我们回想一下
to theory so we're back to juda theory
after many weeks and so let's recall the
我们得出一些p点的Drude方程等于f只是牛顿方程
Drude equation that we derived some p
dot equals f just newton's equations
拖曳项p超过tau，我们可以将其写成电子或
with a drag term p over tau and we can
write that out for electrons or
电子，我们将拥有我所拥有的电子的质量
electrons
we will have mass of the electron I'm
要在这里加一个星星乘以V点，所以唯一与我们不同的是
going to put a star here times V dot so
the only thing different from what we
学期开始时做的是我现在在质量旁边放一颗星，所以
did at the beginning of the term is I'm
now putting a star next to the mass so
它是带底部的有效曲率
it's it's the effective mass the
curvature at the bottom of the band that
不管裸电子质量有多大，
matters not the bare electron mass
there's not an important quantity in a
半导体或绝缘体将具有通常的力
semiconductor or an insulator it will
have the force the usual the usual
永远与您同在的洛伦兹力量永远不会再有一个笑话
Lorentz force which is always with you
there's a another joke all right never
心神
mind
电子的tau大于电子的散射时间，因此
the over tau for the electron the
scattering time for the electron so this
应该看起来很熟悉，这就是我们得出的运输方程
should look fairly familiar this is the
drew de transport equation that we had
在有一些加速度和质量乘以加速度之前，有一些
before there's some acceleration and
mass times acceleration there's some
力在电子上有负E的电荷，有洛伦兹力，
force there's a charge of minus E on the
electron there's a Lorentz force and
无论我们在谈论什么，这里都有一个阻力
there's a drag force here this equation
holds true whether we're talking about
在带的底部附近的电子或在带的顶部附近的电子
an electron near the bottom of band or
an electron near the top of the band
但是，在波段的顶部附近，质量的符号变为负，
however near the top of the band the
sign of the mass gets to be negative and
这似乎有点不可思议，但是如果我们考虑一下它的顶部
that seems a little bit weird
but if we think about it near top of
我们可以考虑考虑到带孔等式，因此在带的顶部附近有一个带
band near top of band a band we can
consider drew to equation for holes so
我们将有一个M星洞乘以相同的洞的速度
we would have an M star hole times the
velocity of the hole same drew to
等式，但孔上的电荷现在为正e再次写等于
equation but the charge on the hole is
now plus e write this again equals plus
e孔上的电荷为正e，那么我们有E加V叉B的力
e the charge on the hole is plus e then
we have E Plus V cross B rents force and
然后，在一定的散射时间内，减去M星孔的速度
then minus M star hole velocity of the
hole over some scattering time for the
也有孔，所以我们在带顶部的孔有一个judor方程
hole as well so we have a judor equation
for the holes at the top of the band as
现在，请记住，我们这里有两件事我们有两个方程式
well now remember that the we have two
things here we have two equations one
对于电子，对于空穴，两个方程的差是
for the electrons one for the holes and
the difference in the two equations is
电荷的符号对于空穴上的电子是不同的
that the sign of the charge is different
for the electrons on the holes but also
M星孔被定义为电子的负M星，因此实际上这些
M star hole was defined to be minus M
star of the electron so in fact these
如果两个方程正好乘以两个方程
two equations are exactly the
if this equation has been multiplied by
整个负1 / m星整个是负电子m星，所以实际上
an overall minus 1/m star whole is minus
m star the electron and so it's actually
只是重复完全相同的Drude方程，所以实际上
just repeating exactly the same Drude
equation so this is actually quite
重要的是，我刚才在这里写的那句话完全一样
important it's exactly the same
statement that I just wrote over here
无论您说的是什么，国家的动态都是完全相同的
the dynamics of the state are exactly
the same whether you're talking about an
电子移动这种状态或空穴移动的状态不存在
electron moving this state or a hole
moving the state the absence of an
电子，轨道是否仍以相同的动力学运动
electron the orbital still moves with
the same dynamics whether or not the
轨道充满了一个电子好，所以关于
orbital is filled with an electron okay
good so the thing that's funny about the
这些半导体中的犹大方程式是
the Judah equation in these
semiconductors is if you're up at the
在乐队的顶部，您可以选择看起来似乎都有点的两件事
top of the band you have a choice of two
things that both seemed a little bit
一种奇怪的可能性是，您必须考虑负质量
weird one possibility is that you have
to think about a negative mass for the
电子，如果您正在考虑状态中的电子
electrons if you're thinking about
electrons in the state the other
可能是您考虑了积极的质量漏洞，但现在这些都是积极的
possibility is you think about positive
mass holes but now these are positively
带电粒子现在可以解决我们的旧难题之一
charged particles now this resolves one
of our old puzzles old puzzle from the
学期老难题的第二天或第三天，这就是为什么霍尔的迹象
second day or the third day of term old
puzzle which was why is sign of Hall
系数霍尔系数有时为正，因此您会记得
coefficients Hall coefficient sometimes
positive so you'll recall that we
根据犹大理论得出，霍尔系数是电荷的n倍以上的1
derived in judah theory that the hall
coefficient is 1 over n times the charge
在粒子周围运动时，这是电子上的电荷，因此，如果您有一个
on the particle moving around this is a
charge on the electron so if you have a
几乎是空的带，它们只是几个电子在运动
band which is mostly empty and they're
just a couple of electrons are moving
周围有犹大理论，这些电子像
around then you have Judah theory for
these electrons moving around just like
我们在一开始就以索末菲理论或犹大理论思考过
we thought about in Sommerfeld theory or
in judah theory at the beginning of the
学期，您将获得一个为负的停止系数，但如果您有异动症
term and you'll get a halt coefficient
which is negative but if you have afib
而且大部分都被填充了，在顶部您只剩下几个孔
and which is mostly filled and you just
have a couple of holes in the top of the
乐队跑来跑去，无论哪种方式，您对它的看法如何
band running around then either way you
look at it what do you think about it as
带有正电荷的孔，或者您认为它是
holes running around with a positive
charge or you think about it as
电子到处跑，但是现在电子的质量是负的
electrons running around but now the
mass of the electron is negative what
你会得到的是，你会得到相反的符号，因为现在携带东西的东西
you'll get is you'll get the opposite
sign because now the things carrying the
充电有错误的信号，他们已经暂停
charge have have the wrong sign they
have pause
号而不是负号，所以这是您知道犹大可能要做的是
sign instead of negative sign so this is
what you know Judah might have to do is
可以回溯到1901年
to way back in 1901 that it appeared
that for some materials for some reason
电荷携带者的标志有误，实际上这就是其中的原因
the charge carrier had the wrong sign
and indeed that's what's going on in
在某些材料中，电荷是由空穴而非电子携带的，因此，如果您
some materials the charge is carried by
holes rather than electrons so if you
有半导体，而你掺杂了电子，你总会得到
have a semiconductor and you and you
dope it with electrons you always get
整个系数的这个符号如果您用孔掺杂它，您将得到
this sign of the whole coefficient if
you dope it with holes you'll get the
现在对金属来说，霍尔系数的符号相反
opposite sign of the Hall coefficient
now for metals real you know real metals
例如钙，铍，锰或类似的东西
like calcium or beryllium or manganese
or something like that which are not
只是轻掺杂，他们知道我们有一些复杂的能带结构
just lightly doped where they you know
we have some complicated band structure
目前尚不清楚应该发出什么信号，因为您可以
it's less clear what the sign of this is
supposed to come out as because you can
就像上次讲课中我们讨论过的钙一样，
have a situation like we discussed with
calcium in the last lecture where you
有一个部分充满的路易斯乐队和一个部分充满的最高乐队，所以您可以
have a partially filled Louis band and a
partially filled highest band so you can
认为它在第一个青铜器中有一些孔，在第一个青铜器中有一些孔
think of it as having some holes in the
first bronze own some holes in the first
带，但是第二个带中有一些电子，所以空穴正试图给你
band but some electrons in the second
band so the holes are trying to give you
霍尔系数为正时，第二个带中的电子正在尝试
a positive Hall coefficient the
electrons in the second band are trying
给你一个负的霍尔系数，因为他们两个互相竞争
to give you a negative Hall coefficient
to the two of them compete with each
其他，然后您必须开始担心哪个具有更大的
other and then you have to start
worrying about which one has a greater
散布时间还可以，所以对于实际而言，它变得有点复杂
scattering time okay so it gets a little
bit more complicated for real for
真正的真正金属，例如铍或锰或钙，但对于
genuine real metals like beryllium or or
manganese or calcium but in the case of
掺杂的半导体，如果您基本上有电子，就会非常清楚地显示出来
a doped semiconductor it comes out very
clearly if you have basically electron
如果你基本上有空洞，你会得到霍尔系数的这个符号
transport you get this sign of the Hall
coefficient if you have basically hole
到目前为止，您的霍尔系数的符号相反
transport you have the opposite sign of
the Hall coefficient so far so good
所以我们解决了这个难题，当我提到其他问题时
so we've resolved this one puzzle there
was something else that I mentioned when
我们在学期开始时就一直谈论Garuda理论
we talked about Garuda theory all the
way back at the beginning of the term
请记住，犹大理论非常有效，对于半导体行业来说
remember the Judah theory works well
works well for semiconductors for
半导体为什么除了可以得到信号的事实
semiconductors why is that besides the
fact that it can get the sign
明智地选择犹大理论的原因
intelligently the reason why Judah
Theory works particularly well for
半导体是因为通常在您谈论半导体时
semiconductors is because usually when
you're talking about semiconductors
您正在谈论的载流子密度非常低
you're talking about a very low density
of charge carriers you're talking about
导带中只有几个电子或化合价中只有几个空穴
just a few electrons in the conduction
band or just a few holes in the valence
带是否因为密度低而低
band because
because density is low is low whether
我们说的是导带中的电子或化合价中的空穴
we're talking about electrons in the
conduction band or holes in the valence
乐队的密度相当低，为什么这会帮助您犹大的原因
band the density is fairly low and why
does that help you the reason that Judah
我们第一次学习理论失败了，是因为我们
Theory failed back when we were studying
it for the first time is because we
忽略了费米统计，而忽略了电子是
neglected Fermi statistics we neglected
the fact that the electrons were
费米子，这使我们搞砸了所有这些东西，例如热容
fermions and that made us mess up all of
these things like the the heat capacity
我们完全错了，因为我们忽略了费米的统计资料，但是如果
we got that completely wrong because we
neglected Fermi statistics but if the
密度真的很低，您实际上有权忽略费米统计量，为什么
density is really low you're actually
entitled to neglect Fermi statistics why
如果有两个电子的概率落在
is that well if the probability of
having two electrons ever sit in the
同一轨道非常低，因为这些电子的密度非常高
same orbital is extremely low because
the density of these electrons is very
低，那么您可以将它们视为经典粒子Maxwell Boltzmann
low then you can just treat these as
classical particles Maxwell Boltzmann
微粒可能是因为它们不太可能会坐在
particles could because it's very
unlikely they're going to sit in the
相同的轨道，首先是一种更好定义的表达方式
same orbital and in the first place a
sort of better defined way of saying
在给定密度的情况下，费米能量即为
that is the Fermi energy given this
density the Fermi energy increases with
如果密度低，则费米能量低如果密度低，则费米能量低
density if the density is low the Fermi
energy is low if the Fermi energy is
比密度低时的温度要低得多
much less than the temperature which
would be true if the density is low then
您不必担心费米统计信息就可以处理粒子
you don't have to worry about Fermi
statistics you can treat the particles
因为是经典的浸泡方式，所以颗粒是经典的，所以您可以
as being classical soaking so particles
are classical are classical and you can
仅考虑常规的经典德鲁伊和经典的玻尔兹曼动力学理论
consider just regular classical Druid a
theory classical Boltzmann dynamics
Maxwell Boltzmann分布而不必担心费米分布
Maxwell Boltzmann distribution without
worrying about Fermi distributions so
这是是的，是要做什么，是的，我们将在稍后介绍这个问题，但是
this is yes what do to hold yes holes
will we'll come to that in a moment but
孔也确实服从我的统计数据，只有在考虑了
holes also do obey for me statistics you
can only put if you think about it for a
第二步，如果您以
second you can only put one hole in a
particular K State if you start with the
价带已满，一旦不能再取出就可以取出
valence band filled you can take it out
once you can't take it out again okay
是的，孔确实服从了费米的统计，他们是费米子，所以这是
yes holes do obey Fermi statistics they
are fermions all right so this is
实际上将我们带到了统计力学领域，或者
actually bringing us to the to the realm
of statistical mechanics or
我们粒子在半导体中的热力学，所以我们必须开始
thermodynamics of our particles in in
semiconductors so we have to start
考虑诸如从中激发多少电子
thinking about things like how many
how many electrons get excited from the
价带到导带，它们如何到达那里，它们是什么
valence band to the conduction band how
did they get there and what are they
他们一旦到达那里，温度就会受到什么影响，所以一件事
doing once they're there what's the
effect of temperature so one thing that
我在上一讲中告诉您，我应该多一点
I told you from the in the last lecture
that I should be a little bit more
老实说我们要回去思考一下掺杂问题，以及如何
honest about we're going to go back to
think about doping for a second and how
掺杂受温度掺杂和温度的影响，所以让我们回想一下
doping is affected by temperature doping
and temperature okay so let's recall
当我们结束时，像磷磷一样打开和打开
that when we took a end opened and
opened like like phosphorus voss in
硅和掺杂剂，我们写道磷等于硅加一
silicon and dopant we wrote that
phosphorus equals a silicon plus one
质子加一个电子，我告诉你电子进入传导
proton plus one electron and I told you
the electron goes into the conduction
带到导带，我告诉你忽略了
band into conduction band band and I
told you to ignore the fact that there's
一个额外的质子现在可以忽略这个问题，可以忽略额外的质子
an extra proton ignore now this issue of
being able to ignore the extra proton
我们另外加上的东西实际上是我们必须要做的
that we put in in addition that is
something that is actually we have to be
多注意一点，我们必须担心温度和
a little bit more careful about and we
have to worry about temperature and
问这样的事情是否可以忽略它，所以请考虑
things like that to ask whether it's
it's okay to ignore it so think about
稍微小心一点，我们放一个质子，放一个电子
this a little bit more carefully we put
in a proton and we put in an electron so
当您将它们放在一起时，电子和质子是做什么的
what is an electron and a proton do when
you put them together what's really
即将发生的事情是您将要形成一个氢原子或氢学术分子
going to happen is you're going to form
form a hydrogen atom or hydrogen academ
氢原子，我们将电子置于导带中，但我们也将
hydrogenic atom we put the electron in
the conduction band but we also put a
后面带正电荷，电子将购买正电荷
positive charge behind and the electron
is going to buy into that positive
电荷被库仑相互作用吸引到该正电荷，所以您
charge it's attracted to that positive
charge by Coulomb interaction so you
形成氢原子，但它不是普通的氢原子
form a hydrogen atom but it's not a
regular hydrogen atom it's slightly
与氢原子不同，因为一个M星不是M不是质量
different from a hydrogen atom because
one M star not M not the mass of the
电子是电子的有效质量，而不是电子的质量
electron it's the effective mass of the
electron not the mass of electron the
M在导带中运动的电子动力学由M给出
dynamics of the electron running around
in the conduction band is given by M
恒星不是电子的裸质量，所以差一
star not the bare mass of the electron
so that's difference one
第二个区别是您在库仑中学到的东西
the second difference is something you
learned in a.m. in the Coulomb
相互作用吸引质子的能量在4 PI epsilon上平方
interaction the attraction back to the
proton is e squared over 4 PI epsilon
零ε相对时间RRε相对介电常数
naught epsilon relative times R R
epsilon a relative dielectric constant
相对介电常数不是通常的4 PIε的平方而不是R
relative dielectric constant not the
usual a squared over 4 PI epsilon not R
好了，库仑相互作用被相对介电常数降低了
ok so the the Coulomb interaction is is
reduced by the relative dielectric
恒定，因为您生活在半导体中，而不是生活在真空中
constant because you're living in a
semiconductor not living in the vacuum
空间，所以如果您还记得我们是规则氢原子，规则氢
of outer space so if you recall we're
regular hydrogen atom regular hydrogen
规则的氢原子有一个结合能e结合
regular hydrogen atom there's a binding
energy e binding which is well ok you
也许很好，也许还记得这个公式，它是8 epsilon naughter squared
probably well maybe do remember this
formula it's 8 epsilon naught squared
普朗克常数平方，但您可能还记得魔术数字
Planck's constant squared but you
probably remember the magic number
十三点六e V是一个孤峰，所以这是a的结合能
thirteen point six e V which is a rid
berg so this is the binding energy of a
规则氢原子，但在半导体中的结合能e
regular hydrogen atom but in a
semiconductor the binding energy e
电子与质子的结合将我放的额外电荷
binding of the electron back to the
proton the additional charge that I put
现在掺杂物中的M星电子e超过8 epsil
in with the dopant is now M star
electron e to the fourth over 8 epsilon
H平方上没有相对的ε平方，然后我可以写成M星
relative epsilon naught squared over H
squared which I can then write as M star
电子的质量除以电子的质量乘以ε的1
of the electron divided by the mass of
the electrons times 1 over epsilon
相对平方时间13.6 TV现在，此表达式可能有很大不同
relative squared times 13.6 TV now this
expression can be a whole lot different
从13.6电视开始，通常情况下它会小很多
from 13.6 TV and generically it's going
to be a lot smaller typically effective
电子和半导体的质量可以是电子质量的三分之一
masses of electrons and semiconductors
can be a third of the mass of an
电子甚至可以是电子质量的十分之一甚至更小
electron it can be even a tenth of the
mass with electron or even smaller the
电常数半导体可以是
die
electric constant semiconductors can be
像10这样的数字，这意味着该数字的实际结合能
numbers like 10 so that means that this
number the actual binding energy of the
电子到半导体中的质子可能是一个因素
electron to the proton in the
semiconductor can be as much as a factor
比这少一千分之一
of a thousand less than this for example
in silicon in silicon key binding of the
对于电子伏特来说，回到其掺杂核的电子为0.04
electron back to its dopant nucleus is
0.04 for electron volts a much much much
较小的数字，现在为什么这么重要好吧，哦，看这个
smaller number now why is that important
okay oh look at this
我需要学院把它放在这里，我要画画，所以这是底部
I need that Academy put this in here I'm
going to draw the so here's the bottom
导带的这里是价带的顶部，所以当您添加掺杂剂时
of the conduction band here's the top of
a valence band so when you put a dopant
当你把磷掺杂剂形成一个结合态
in when you put the phosphorous dopant
in you form a bound state which is a
导带底部下方的结合距离非常短
very small distance a binding be binding
below the bottom of the conduction band
因此，通过绑定而不是仅仅坐在K上，您可以获得一点能量
so you gain a tiny bit of energy by
binding instead of just sitting with K
在导带中等于零，您可以通过束缚获得一点能量
equals zero in the conduction band you
gain a little bit of energy by binding
到你来自的正核
to the positive nucleus that you came
from
但是这里的能量很小，在室温下
however this energy here is very very
small and at room temperature at room
温度降到t室时，电子自由断裂，自由断裂，
temperature is down at t room the
electron breaks free breaks free and
进入导带，自由破裂并进入导带
goes off into the conduction band breaks
free and goes into conduction band
它只是被热激发到导带中，这就是为什么
it's just thermally excited into the
conduction band and this is why this is
为什么在我们向硅添加磷掺杂时可以考虑一下
why it's okay to think about when we add
phosphorus doping to silicon we really
应该只考虑室温或更高的温度
should just think a on room temperature
or a higher temperature we should think
关于这只是将电子直接添加到导带中，如果
about this is just directly adding
electrons into the conduction band if
你把它冷却一下如果我把它冷却一下也许我会写下来
you cool it down if you cool this maybe
I'll write that down
因此，掺杂增加了电子，直接增加了
so doping adds electrons adds directly
to
-导带或类似的（如果在添加时对孔做相同的事情）
- conduction band or similarly if you do
the same thing with holes when you add
在孔中，它将与上的负电荷形成束缚态
in the hole it would form a bound state
to the to the negative charge on the
我们留下的核被放入硼，铝或
nucleus that we left behind we're
putting in a boron or an aluminum or
在有限的温度下，空穴会脱离其原子核并运行
something and at finite temperature that
hole breaks free of its nucleus and runs
进入价带，但是在低温下
off into the valence band however at low
temperature at low temperature the
电子变得被束缚，变得被束缚，再次被束缚到掺杂核
electron becomes becomes bound becomes
bound again bound to the dopant nucleus
再次掺杂核，所以如果您要测量
to dopant nucleus nucleus again so if
you were measuring the density of
如果您将系统完全冷却，则导带中的电子
electrons in the conduction band
if you cooled the system down a lot all
突然间，您会发现传导中的电子密度
of a sudden you would discover that the
density of electrons in the conduction
能带下降是因为所有这些电子都被冻结回到
band was dropping because all of these
electrons were getting frozen back onto
他们由此产生的核被称为载体冻结
their the nucleus that they came from
this is known as carrier freeze-out
运营商冻结了，好吧，到目前为止，很好，每个人都对此感到满意
carrier freeze-out okay all right so so
far so good everyone happy with this all
对，现在是时候认真思考一下统计力学了
right so now it's time to do some
serious statistical mechanics thinking
关于我们在导带中应该有多少个电子或多少个空穴
about how many electrons we should have
in the conduction band or how many holes
我们应该在价带中有一个相当重要的计算
we should have in the valence band this
is a rather important calculation that
实际上经常出现在考试中，所以这是一件好事
actually shows up on exams very
frequently so it's a good thing to go
好几次，所以让我们从这种通用
through several times all right so let's
a start with this sort of generic
导带底部的图片价带顶部的图片
picture of the bottom of a conduction
band the top of a valence band
他们通常不必放出相同的曲率
they don't have to have the same
curvature in general they put out
我已经画出了不同的有效质量
different effective masses I've drawn
the effective mass is being slightly
不同的是他们不必对齐，这可能是间接的差距
different they don't have to be aligned
the it could be an indirect gap the top
价带的可能与底部的位置不同
of the valence band could be in a
different place than the bottom of the
导带，我们称之为能量e导通
conduction band we'll call this energy e
conduction
传导中的ec4将称此能量ev 4e价称此能量e间隙C子G
ec4 in conduction will call this energy
e v 4e valence this energy e gap C sub G
和E间隙等于e传导-价，我们可以想象化学
and E gap equals e conduction - valence
and we'll imagine that the chemical
潜力在乐队的中间，我们将尝试找出
potential is somewhere in the middle of
the band and we'll try to figure out
没关系，所以我们从价带开始
where it is all right and so the we
start with the valence band being
完全填满，我们将尝试弄清楚添加时会发生什么
completely filled and we're going to try
to figure out what happens when we add
温度，所以我们需要做的几件事是光谱
temperature so a couple of things we're
going to need one is what the spectra
因此，对于我们的能量大于能量传导，我们拥有的能量是
are so for our energy greater than
energy conduction we have energy it's
这些能量传导的K函数+ H bar平方K-K min平方超过2m
function of K these energy conduction +
H bar squared K - K min squared over 2m
星形电子，然后对于能量小于化合价的能量，我们有倒置的空间
star electron and then for energy less
than a valence we have the upside-down
抛物线ek等于evi减去H bar平方K-K max平方超过2m m星
parabola ek equals evince minus H bar
squared K - K max squared over 2m m star
整体+ M星整体记住正，我们曲率负
whole + M star whole remember is
positive we have a negative curvature of
乐队的顶端，然后我们必须考虑数国家
the top of the band and then we have to
think about counting States so counting
状态，我们会回想起我们对自由电子进行Sommerfeld理论的时间
States and we'll think back to when we
did Sommerfeld theory for free electrons
对于自由电子，我们的能量很好，e等于H bar平方K
for free electrons we had well our
energy was e equals H bar squared K
平方超过2m且状态密度为单位的状态密度
squared over 2m and the density of
states so the density of states per unit
e的体积阱G由该表达式给出，我们将其计算为质量
volume well G of e was given by this
expression which we calculated to mass
到2 pi平方的H条立方化epsilon的三分之二到1/2
to the three-halves over 2 pi squared H
bar cubed epsilon to the 1/2 we
我在学期的第二天或第三天计算了这个
calculated this I think on the second or
third day of the term this is the
单位体积中状态的密度
density of states out of states per unit
volume
每卷的状态，因此我们希望使用完全相同的计算，除了
States per volume so we'd like to use
exactly the same calculation except for
导带和价带，所以实际上没有做功
the conduction band and the valence band
here so without actually doing the work
很容易看到随着密度的增加会产生什么结果
it's pretty easy to see what the result
is going to come out as the density of
e大于e的导带中的状态将是
states in the conduction band for e
greater than e conduction is going to be
电子的质量到三分之二除以相同的两个π
to mass of the electrons star to the
three-halves divided by the same two pi
平方H立方，并且一半的e相同，但是e减去e
squared H bar cubed and there's the same
e to the one-half but it's e minus e
导带，因此您正在测量相对于底部的能量
conduction band so you're measuring the
energy with respect to the bottom of the
导带抛物线从导带的底部开始，但
conduction band the parabola starts at
the bottom of the conduction band but
否则，这与人们满意的计算完全相同
otherwise it's exactly the same
calculation people happy with that okay
好，所以G价可能会稍微复杂一些，但不会太多
good so G valence may be a little bit
more complicated but not too much more
复杂的是要在两个pi平方高的H条上将M星孔分成三等分
complicated is to M star hole
three-halves over two pi squared H bar
立方，在这里我们测量EEEME，它可用于1/2和
cubed and here we measure
eeeem itís available to the 1/2 and
我们正在测量向下的方向，我们需要这个东西
we're measuring going in the downward
direction well we need this thing to the
1/2是一个正数，所以它必须是价数减去e（我们测量下降）
1/2 to be a positive number so it has to
be valence minus e we measure going down
下降到低能耗状态，我们得到的州越来越多
we get an increasing number of states as
we go down to lower energy good alright
那么我们可以写导带
so then we can write in conduction band
我们只是用统计力学来计算电子密度n
we just use our statistical mechanics
the density of electrons density n of
安逸的电子由n作为T的函数给出，即N等于
electrons of ease is given by n as a
function of T that's an N equals the
从导带底部到能量无穷大的积分
integral from the bottom of the
conduction band up to energy infinity
状态的能量密度与能量和紧实度的关系
the energy density of states as a
function of energy and the firming
β能量减去mu ok，所以状态密度的积分是
factor beta energy minus mu ok so the
integral of the density of states is
基本上是所有本征态的总和，费米因子可能是
basically a sum over all eigenstates and
the fermi factor is the probably
我会把状态填满，所以这只是数所有
that i ghen state is going to be filled
so this is just counting up all the
在给定温度下填充的状态，但我们需要知道
states that are filled at a given
temperature but we need to know what the
化学势还可以，所以现在我们要写出费米
chemical potential is okay so now we're
going to well let's write out the Fermi
费米函数是β能量减去mu加的一倍以上
function here the Fermi function is one
over e to the beta energy minus mu plus
现在，如果我们处于相当高的温度下或者密度低，或者
one now if if we're at a fairly high
temperature or if the density is low or
严格来说，我们需要的是β能量减去mu大于1
strictly speaking what we need is beta
energy minus mu is much greater than one
这意味着mu远低于EC以下的远低于意指低于at
this means that mu is much below much
below below EC meaning that below by at
最少的温度，所以您知道低于
least the amount of the temperature so
you know fairly well below the the
导带的底部，这很容易，因为
bottom of the conduction band and that's
pretty easy because the gaps between the
导带和价带可以有几个电子伏特
conduction band and the valence band
there can be a couple of electron volts
比典型温度大得多，这意味着可以近似得出NF
much bigger than typical temperatures
that means that NF can be approximated
好的，您基本上可以删除加号，而得到的只是
by well you basically can just drop the
plus one and you get the just the
常规的玻尔兹曼因数这是麦克斯韦的倍数
regular Boltzmann factor this is just
multiple on Maxwell Boltzmann Maxwell
玻尔兹曼，让我们输入，我们有n个T，那么它将是整数
Boltzmann so let's put that in and we
have n of T then is going to be integral
d能量0对不起EC从导带的底部一直到G的无穷大
d energy 0 sorry EC from the bottom of
the conduction band up to infinity of G
能量，然后将麦克斯韦玻尔兹曼因子e减去负β能量减去
of energy and then the Maxwell Boltzmann
factor e to the minus beta energy minus
亩近似值，这是温度，那么我们该怎么做
mu making that approximation and this is
temperature then how do we do this
我们要做的第一件事就是要做好我们要做的事情
integral well first thing we're going to
do is we're going to well what are we
我们要写出这个G是什么，所以它有一颗2m星
going to do we're going to write out
what this G is so this has a 2m star of
电子到三等分，它有一个2 pi平方的H形立方体，这个
the electron to the three-halves and it
has a 2 pi squared H bar cubed and this
积分能量能量导带
integral the energy energy the
conduction band
dx e- e传导到1/2，然后e到负β能量-mu
the d x e- e conduction to the 1/2 and
then e to the minus beta energy minus mu
所以这是我们在那里的1/2的e，我们必须进行积分
so this is the e to the 1/2 that we have
up there and we have to do this integral
而我们进行积分的方法是将e减去负数
and the way we do this integral is by
shifting out a factor of e to the minus
βEC在前面减去mu，所以我们剩下EC的积分d能量
beta EC minus mu out front so then we're
left with an integral d energy from EC
到无穷大u减去EC到1/2，然后e到减去beta e减去EC
to infinity u minus EC to the 1/2 and
then e to the minus beta e minus EC
很好，如果我们想要x等于E减去EC，那么我们可以写
which is nice we can then write if we
want well x equals E minus EC if we want
所以这成为DX的整数，从0到无穷大X到1/2 e到负数
so this becomes integral of DX from 0 to
infinity X to the 1/2 e to the minus
beta X，那么我们可以通过定义y平方等于x来进行积分
beta X then we can do that integral by
defining y squared equals x this becomes
一个简单的高斯积分，我们得到β减去三分之二的平方
a simple Gaussian integral and we get
beta the minus three-halves times square
pi的根超过2可以，所以我们将它们放在一起，最终得到
root of pi over 2 okay so we put that
all together and we end up getting the
然后，导带中电子的密度与T的关系为
density of electrons in the conduction
band as a function of T is then putting
所有这些因素加起来，是PI H bar上电子星KBT质量的1/4
together all those factors 1/4 to mass
of the electron star KBT over PI H bar
等于三分之二的e到负β能量的导带
squared to the three-halves e to the
minus beta energy the conduction band of
减去亩，这就是我们的表达式，我们现在知道其中有多少个电子
minus mu so this is our expression we
now know how many electrons there are in
导带是温度的函数，是MU的函数
the conduction band is a function of
temperature and is a function of MU the
重要的是要带走一些前提因素，不是
important thing to take away there's
some pre factors here which aren't that
至关重要的是这里要带走的重要东西基本上是被激活的
crucial the important thing here to take
away is is basically activated that you
必须激活从化学势到传导的能量
have to activate the energy up from the
chemical potential into the conduction
带，以便当您使电子下降时将电子带入导带
band in order to get an electron into
the conduction band as you drop the
温度导带中的电子数将下降
temperature the number of electrons in
the conduction band is going to drop
到目前为止，一切都很好，现在我们必须做同样的事情
exponentially okay all right so far so
good now we have to do the same thing
对于漏洞，我认为我们仍然可以及时做到
for holes I think we can still do this
in time
价带中的孔数好吧，让我们写下来
the number of holes in the valence band
well okay let's write that that's going
从负无穷大到价带D能量的顶部积分
to be integral from minus infinity to
the top of the valence band D energy the
在价带中的状态密度，然后我写1减去费米
density of states in the valence band
and then I'll write 1 minus the Fermi
价带βepsilon减去nu减去我的因子-为什么这么好
factor in the valence band beta epsilon
minus nu minus me--it why is that well
如果电子为状态的概率为费米函数，则
if the probability of an electron being
a state is the Fermi function then the
空穴为无电子状态的概率为1减去
probability of a hole being the state
the absence of electron is 1 minus the
Fermi的功能还不错，所以在这里我们基本上要考虑这个因素
Fermi function good all right so this
factor here we're going to basically go
通过相同的操作，所以这可以写成1减去1等于e
through the same manipulation so this is
we can write this as a 1 minus 1 over e
到beta epsilon的是mu加1会消失哦我的空间不足
to the beta epsilon is mu plus 1 that
becomes out oh I'm running out of space
我不是很好吗，这东西变成这个
aren't I
all right well this thing becomes this
整个事情在这里变成1比1加e到负beta e减去mu
whole thing here becomes 1 over 1 plus e
to the minus beta e minus mu that maybe
采取了两个步骤，但是您可以代数检查这是正确的
took two steps but but you can check
algebraically that's true and again
我们将假设类似于我有更多空间的东西
we're going to assume something
analogous to what do I have more space
某个地方可能没有，也许我不是，所以我们要假设一些事情
somewhere no all right maybe I don't so
we're going to assume something
类似于我们对电子的假设，将假设化学物质
analogous to what we assumed for the
electrons will assume that the chemical
电位不太接近太接近太近意味着内部
potential is not too close too close too
close meaning within the within the
在价带顶部的KBT范围内的温度
temperature within a range of KBT of the
top of the valence band
evie在这种情况下，可以将此事物近似为整个事物
evie in which case this thing can be
approximated as this whole thing here
可以近似等于βepsilon的玻尔兹曼因子e
can be approximately equal to the
Boltzmann factor e to the beta epsilon
减去亩少于1好吧，所以还是差不多
minus mu of much less than 1 okay so
it's again more or less the same the
同样的故事，但在这里您必须意识到能量更少
same story but here
you have to realize that energy is less
比起您，您正在整个激活价带向下
than you and you're activating a whole
downwards into the valence band rather
而不是电子进入导带
than a electron up into the conduction
band
因此插入价带状态密度的表达式
so plugging in the expression for the
density of states of the valence band
我们得到了一个三分之二的pi平方H形立方体的星洞
we get to I'm a star hole to the
three-halves to pi squared H bar cubed
积分D能量减去无穷大至可见性
integral D energy minus infinity to
evince
e价减去e的1/2 e减去mu并完全相同
e valence minus e the 1/2 e to the beta
epsilon minus mu and exactly the same
我认为在各个地方可能都带有几个减号的操纵
manipulations with maybe a couple minus
signs put in in various places I think
你应该做功课，所以也许我不会经历，而且我
you're supposed to do it for homework so
maybe I won't go through it and also I'm
真的提前了，所以整个事情在一天结束时变得非常
really ahead of time so this whole thing
becomes at the end of the day a very
与上面发现的类似表达是PI上1/4-M星整个KBT
analogous expression to what we found
above is 1/4 - M star whole KBT over PI
H bar减去负数mu的均方根为e的三分之二。
H bar squared all to three-halves e to
the minus beta mu minus e valence and
同样，您在这里有一些前置因素，但重要的是
again it's the same story you have some
pre factors here but the important part
是您必须激活从化学势到
is that you have to activate a hole down
from the chemical potential into the
价带，因为它需要能量才能将一个孔推入价
valence band because it takes energy to
push on a hole down into the valence
带孔要尽可能多地上升，所以如果我们知道化学物质
band the holes want to go up as much as
possible so if we knew the chemical
势，我们知道温度，我们可以算出密度
potential and we knew the temperature we
could figure out the density of
导带中的电子和价带中的空穴密度
electrons in the conduction band and the
density of holes in the valence band but
现在有一个诀窍，诀窍是看T的n乘以P的乘积
now there's a trick and the trick is to
look at the product of n of T times P of
这样做，我们得到了很多因素，因此比PI H高出1/2 KB
T let's do that we get a bunch of
factors so 1/2 out front KB T over PI H
正方形的立方，然后有一个质量为整个恒星的电子恒星-
bar squared cubed then there's a mass of
an electron star mass of whole star -
三分之二，然后看一下指数因子，您会发现
three-halves and then if you look at the
exponential factors you'll notice that
负beta Muse的指数因子e和正beta mu的指数因子
the exponential factors e to the minus
beta Muse and the e to the plus beta mu
将取消，因此剩下的唯一东西是e到负beta e
will cancel so the only thing that's
left over is e to the minus beta e
传导-有效eeeek诱导-e价是egapp，所以
conduction - avail
eeeek induction - e valence is egapp so
如果您知道间隙能量并且知道温度，那么您将知道
if you know the gap energy and you know
the temperature you know the product of
导带中的电子数和空穴数
the number of electrons in the
conduction band and the number of holes
在价带中，这条法则非常重要，被称为上帝
in the valence band and this this law
very important law is known as God is
如果您与化学家交谈，则被称为质量作用定律。
known as the law of mass action law of
mass action if you talk to chemists they
知道这是他们的集体行动法则，因此命名法
know this they have a law of mass action
and the nomenclature comes from this
从化学上来说，实际上我可能不会讲究为什么它被称为相同
from chemistry actually I won't maybe go
through why it is it's called the same
是化学中的质量作用定律，但这里很重要
thing as the law of mass action in
chemistry but the important thing here
要意识到的是，该产品与化学势无关
to realize is that the product is
independent of the chemical potential
这意味着它与我们掺杂系统的方式无关，所以让我们
and that means it's independent of how
we've doped the system so let's a couple
如果我们有一个内在的话，还有更多的事情哦
more things if we have an intrinsic Oh
did I use that word I never use that
这样的本征之前的单词表示没有掺杂，所以如果我有本征半导体
word before so intrinsic means undoped
so if I have an intrinsic semiconductor
我应该在上一堂课中用那个词来表示内在的
I should have probably used that that
word in last lecture for an intrinsic
半导体导带中电子的密度等于
semiconductor the density of electrons
in the conduction band equals the
价带中空穴的密度，因为每次带电子时
density of holes in the valence band
because each time you take an electron
在价带之外，将其放在导带中，创建一个孔
out of the valence band you put it up in
the conduction band you created one hole
并创造了一个电子，在这种情况下，您只需取
and created one electron in which case
you can just take the square root of the
的质量定律，你可以知道在任何温度下N和P分别是多少
law of mass action and you can tell what
N and P are at any temperature so you're
那里很好，但是对于掺杂的掺杂系统，则更复杂，然后我们添加
good there but for a doped system doped
then it's more complicated then we add
掺杂物，我们在导带中的电子数为负
dopants and we have the number of
electrons in the conduction band minus
价带中的空穴数等于施主杂质的数目
the number of holes in the valence band
equals the number of donor impurities
杂质减去受体杂质数量
impurities minus the number of acceptor
impurities
因为基本上每次您添加施主杂质时，您都会向其中添加一个电子
because basically each time you add a
donor impurity you add one electron into
导带不每次都在价带上加一个孔
the conduction band without adding a
hole into the valence band on each time
您添加一个受体，在价带中添加一个孔，而不添加一个
you add an acceptor you add a hole into
the valence band without adding an
电子进入导带，只要T是
electron into the conduction band and
this is true as long as as long as T is
大于T冻结，其中导带中的电子
greater than T freeze-out where the
electrons in the conduction band gets
绑定到他们的供体上，价带中的空洞被绑定到
get bound to their donors and the holes
in the in the valence band get bound to
他们的受体，所以这里要意识到的关键是N的乘积
their acceptors so the key thing to
realize here is that the product of N
并且P是固定的，与掺杂无关，n NP的差异取决于
and P is fixed independent of the doping
the difference of n NP depends on the
掺杂意味着在添加电子时会添加施主杂质
doping this means that as you add
electrons as you add donor impurities
化学势上升，所以您获得更多的电子和更少的空穴，但是
the chemical potential goes up so you
get more electrons and fewer holes but
电子数乘无数的乘积保持不变
the product of the number of electrons
numberless holes stays fixed as you add
更多的受体化学势下降，您得到的空洞比
more acceptors the chemical potential
goes down you get more holes than
电子，但两者的乘积保持固定，也许我什至会写
electrons but the product of the two
stays fixed maybe I'll even write that
在叫停之前，先增加捐助者，然后亩增加亩。
before calling it quits
adding donors mu goes up mu goes up
我们添加了接受器，接受器的mu下降了，但是由于质量定律
we're adding acceptors acceptors mu goes
down but because of the law of mass
行动这两个的乘积总是会保持固定，所以
action the product of those two is
always going to stay fixed all right so
下次我们会去讨论一些真正的半导体
next time we'll pick up and actually
talk about some real semiconductor
设备和改变世界的设备，例如晶体管，我会看到
devices and the devices that change the
world like the transistor and I'll see
你我认为星期三是星期三我认为是星期三好
you I think Wednesday is Wednesday
I think it's Wednesday okay have a good
周末你
weekend
you